Guide to the William C. Lynch Dennis Brain Collection ARS.0138
Archive of Recorded Sound
William C. Lynch Dennis Brain Collection
circa 1921-2012
ARS.0138
Lynch, William C., 1943-
12 boxes [5.75 linear feet]
12 boxes: Approximately 122 non-commercial compact discs, averaging four separate works per disc; 49 LP recordings; 12 78rpm recording; 33 commercially released compact disc recordings in addition to a special commercially released EMI Classics collection consisting of 58 analog cassette tape recordings; a 13 compact disc special collection retailed in Japan only containing rare works; 5 commercial and non-commercial compact disc recordings of Kaoru Chiba (1928-2008), Dennis Brain’s most prominent student; 4 photographs contributed by Ms. Mako Rova from the United States who attended Kaoru Chiba’s Celebration of Life in Japan at noon, June 28, 2008 at Blue Rose (Small Hall) in Suntory Hall, Minato-ku, Tokyo; 6 books of historical interest pertaining to the “Brain” era complementing the current inventory at the Stanford Library; sheet music in part consisting of rare works performed by Dennis Brain, some of which are no longer obtainable; a photo catalog consisting of numerous commercially licensed photos and non-commercially released photos of Brain including his very early years and while on US tour; research notes from numerous publications about Brain including critic reviews and those from conductors and composers with whom he worked; correspondences and notes pertaining to the Sotheby's auction of Brain's Music Library; a VHS recording showing Brain performing the Beethoven Sonata; a digital and a VHS recording of Brain appearing at the 1955 Edinburgh Festival, filmed on 1 September 1954 at the rehearsal outside Usher Hall narrated by Alistair Simm in which Brain is seen and heard performing the Siegfried Horn Call; other miscellaneous subject matter used as source material in the June 2011 publication of his definitive biography, Dennis Brain: a life in music, University of North Texas Press.
Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound, Stanford University Libraries Stanford, California 94305-3076
The William C. Lynch Dennis Brain Collection consists of commercial and unpublished orchestral and solo recordings on audiocassette, compact disc, 33rpm long play and 78rpm records, VHS video cassette, and DVD, all featuring the world renowned British horn player, Dennis Brain (1921-1957). Also included are research notes, sheet music, photographs, and books pertaining to Dennis Brain from the late 1930’s to his death just prior to September 1957. It also includes research notes pertaining to the publication of the 2011 biography, Dennis Brain: a life in music. The collection is believed to be the largest of its kind, if not the most comprehensive and organized collection of recorded music related to Dennis Brain anywhere in the world.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Source
The William C. Lynch Dennis Brain Collection was donated to the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound by William C. Lynch in 2012.
Scope and Contents of Collection
The William C. Lynch Dennis Brain Collection consists of both commercially released and unpublished recordings of the world renowned British horn player, Dennis Brain (1921-1957), most of which have been obtained via over the air broadcasts. Others are derived from privately recorded performances, on reel-to-reel tape, of solo and orchestral performances from the late 1930s through the late 1950s, which were later transferred onto either disc or alternative tape media. The donated collection differs from other private Dennis Brain collections as: a) most of its contents exists in digital form, b) the collection is well documented by the donor who acquired its contents largely through exchange, on a work-for-work basis, with other collectors throughout the world, which in turn enabled the collection to grow over a period of many years, c) the proliferation of digital technology and the extent of the Internet which has enabled large numbers of Brain works to be commercially produced and stored on a single digital compact disc by the recording industry. Relational databases now facilitate the search process by providing ready access to a variety of archives including radio stations, libraries, recording studios, music societies, universities, TV broadcast stations, national archives, journals, newspapers, and critic reviews of past era performances, all of which serve to provide an extensive amount of information relating to the life and work of Dennis Brain.
Sources for the collection's audio recordings vary. They include live and recorded off-the-air broadcasts, recorded on tape and then later transferred to compact disc; rebroadcasts from international festivals; commercially released compact disc recordings; compact disc recordings purchased from the British Library Sound Archive; miscellaneous radio stations; various video distributors; the BBC; Stanford University's Archive of Recorded Sound (specifically ARS0124 - Nate Brown Western Sound Archive Collection); Oesterreichischer Rundfunk (ORF), Salzburg; Deutschland Radio; Pathe’ News; the worldwide Dennis Brain collector community; and used record shops throughout the world.
The audio portion of this collection primarily consists of solo and orchestral works performed by Dennis Brain, along with various rehearsal recordings. Many of the solo works included were composed for him by Britain’s leading composers of the day. The collection also includes recorded lectures by Brain related to the early horn and its evolution along with interviews with critics, colleagues, composers, conductors, friends and associates of Brain, and other leading principals of the British music scene as late as December 2011 when BBC Radio 3 featured a broadcast on Dennis Brain during one of its featured programs, Music Matters. Some works within the collection may appear redundant as to the composer. However Brain recorded the same works with different conductors and in his earlier years with different orchestras including the Royal Air Force Symphony Orchestra. More often than not, more than one work or performance is included on a chosen cassette tape or compact disc. Movements are identified on separate compact disc tracks in most cases. In all but a few instances, programs, conductor, orchestra, recording dates and program duration are listed on the compact disc cover. Similar details are also enclosed with the audiocassettes. Also included within the audio collection are five recordings by Kaoru Chiba, Dennis Brain’s most prominent student. His testimony to Brain’s greatness is faithfully reproduced through his writings, consisting of five published papers, also part of this collection.
Brain performed under no less than seventy conductors, eventually becoming conductor of his own wind quintet, wind ensemble and chamber orchestra. He recorded with no fewer than fourteen orchestras and seven string ensembles, The London Mozart Players and The London Wind Ensemble being among the most notable. Brain is heard on the majority of the collection's recordings, including RAF Symphony Orchestra recordings from the war years along with recordings from various London music halls and European music festivals.
Also featured are recordings of Brain as organist. It is little known fact that in addition to being a world renowned horn player, Brain was also an excellent organist, having studied under George Dorrington Cunningham (1878 – 1948), whose others students included E. Power Biggs. Brain is featured as organist on a number of recordings in the collection, including one of the Intermezzo from Cavalleria Rusticana by Mascagni, featuring The Philharmonia Orchestra, conducted by Herbert von Karajan, 24 July 1954. Additional recordings featuring Brain as organist include, A Grand Grand Overture from the Hoffnung Music Festival Concert, Royal Festival Hall, London, 13 November 1956 and an Afrikaans broadcast for "Dingaans Day", 16 December 1940.
Also included in the collection are rare books of the period which served as resource material in the writing of the 2011 biography Dennis Brain: a life in music. The book collection complements those currently residing in the Stanford Library.
Finally, the collection also includes research notes in hard-copy and digital formats, consisting of critic reviews; articles about Brain composed by peers who knew and worked with him, composers, conductors, musicologists and musicians; music journals; international newspapers; professional journals; recording reviews; published academia; sheet music of works performed by Brain; a Sotheby's auction catalog, listing items from Brain’s music library; notes gathered from the Hoover Institution archives pertaining to the war years; BBC wartime broadcasts of Brain works; program notes from a 2002 celebration of Dennis Brain’s 80th birthday; videocassettes and DVDs of movies in which Brain was an orchestral member for the accompanying film music; a private collection of commercial and private photographs; video of a 1955 Edinburgh Festival rehearsal, made in 1954, featuring Brain performing the Siegfried Horn Call; and other miscellaneous documents to aid future researchers in this field.
The collection is believed to be the largest of its kind, if not the most comprehensive and organized collection of recorded music related to Dennis Brain anywhere in the world. It is considered a living donation through which additions to the collection will continue as new recordings and findings pertaining to this extraordinary musician are discovered.
Arrangement
Original order has been maintained as closely as possible.
Indexing Terms
Brain, Dennis, 1921-1957; Horn music; Horn players; Instrumental music
- Audiocassettes, circa 1936-2011; 58 audiocassettes (Audio 5, Audio 4)
  Scope and contents
  The contents of these audiocassettes have been digitized and transferred to CD-R. Please see the non-commercial recordings subseries under the compact disc series for details of these recordings.
- Books and scores, circa 1937-2011; 16 items 7 books; 9 scores
  - Jack Brymer: from where I sit, 1979; 1 book; Cassell, ISBN 0304303135.; Brymer, Jack (Books 10)
  - A devil to play: one man's year-long quest to master the orchestra's most difficult instrument, 2008; 1 book; HarperCollins, ISBN 9780061626616.; Rees, Jasper (Books 10)
  - Music in blue: uniforms of musicians in the Royal Air Force and its predecessor - a photographic history, 2007; 1 book; Eagle and Lyre Publications, ISBN 9780955641503.; Signed by the author.; Singleton, Gilbert A., 1953- (Books 10)
  - Dame Vera Lynn: some sunny day, 2009; 1 book; HarperCollins, ISBN 9780007318155.; Lynn, Vera (Books 10)
  - Proms, the, 1974; 1 book; David and Charles, ISBN 0715366799.; Orga, Ateş (Books 10)
  - Dennis Brain: a biography, 1976; 1 book; Hale, ISBN 070915772X; Britten, Benjamin, 1913-1976; Pettitt, Stephen J., 1945- (Books 10)
  - Dennis Brain: a life in music, 2011; 1 book; University of North Texas Press, ISBN 9781574413076.; Gamble, Stephen, 1963-; Lynch, William C., 1943- (Books 10)
  - Poulenc, Francis, 1899-1963. Elegies, horn, piano, circa 1958; 1 score; Chester Music, ISBN 0711921555.; Poulenc, Francis, 1899-1963 (Books 10)
    Scoring
    Full score and parts
  - Bowen, York, 1884-1961. Sonatas, horn, piano, op. 101, E♭, circa 1993; 1 score; Emerson Edition Ltd, 165.; Bowen, York, 1884-1961 (Books 10)
  - Seiber, Mátyás, 1905-1960. Nocturne, horn, string orchestra, circa 1952; 1 score; Schott, ED10336.; Seiber, Mátyás, 1905-1960 (Books 10)
    Piano reduction and horn part
  - Orchestral studies from operas and concert works: for french horn, 1947; 1 score; International Music Company, 867.; Wagner, Richard, 1813-1883 (Books 10)
  - Orchestral studies from operas and concert works: for french horn, undated; 1 score; International Music Company, 869.; Strauss, Richard, 1864-1949 (Books 10)
  - Strauss, Richard, 1864-1949. Concertos, horn, orchestra, no. 2, E♭ major; arranged, circa 1950; 1 score; Boosey and Hawkes.; Perry, Harold, 1895-1956; Strauss, Richard, 1864-1949 (Books 10)
  - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Concertos, horn, orchestra; Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Konzertsatz, horn, orchestra, K. 371, circa 1960; 1 score; G.Schirmer, 1807.; Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 (Books 10)
    Piano reduction
  - Ravel, Maurice, 1875-1937. Pavane pour une infante défunte, circa 1942; 1 score; Edition Musicus; Ravel, Maurice, 1875-1937 (Books 10)
  - Thirty studies: opus 13, for horn solo, circa 1960; 1 score; International Music Company, 1982.; Gallay, Jacques François, 1795-1864 (Books 10)
  - Unbound scores, circa 1937-1970; 1 folder (Box 11)
    Unbound photocopies of various works for horn, either written for or associated with Brain.
- Compact Discs, circa 1936-2011; 155 discs 123 CD-Rs; 32 compact discs
  - Non-commerical recordings, circa 1936-2011; 117 items 113 CD-Rs; 4 compact discs
    Scope and Contents
    These compact discs principally contain recordings of radio broadcasts that have been dubbed from their original audiocassette format to compact disc. Dennis Brain's involvement in these performances is assumed and therefore his name is not stated in the performance listings unless his involvement was other than that of hornist. The majority of recordings featured here were never published commercially. However, some compilations do feature recordings that were released on various LP or 78rpm disc publications or later commercially released retrospectives.
    - Sharples and Jacob, circa 1951; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 100)
      Tracklisting
      Sharples, Bob, 1919-1987. Waltz Sympathy.
      Sharples, Bob. Will You Remember.
      Jacob, Gordon, 1895-1984. Concertos, horn, string orchestra. Riddick Orchestra; Jacob, Gordon, 1895-1984, conductor. 1951 July 3.
    - Hindemith and Mozart, 1952-1956; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 101)
      Hindemith, Paul, 1895-1963. Sonatas, horn, piano (1939). Mewton-Wood, Noel, 1922-1953, piano. British Broadcasting Corporation, live broadcast. 1953 January 28.
      Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Concertos, horn, orchestra, K. 417, E♭major. Sveriges radios symfoniorkester; Frykberg, Sten, 1910-1983, conductor. Sveriges radio aktiebolag, live broadcast. 1956 October 9.
      Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Concertos, horn, orchestra, K. 447, E♭ major. Süddeutscher Rundfunk. Sinfonie-Orchester; Müller-Kray, Hans, conductor. Live broadcast, 1952 April 20.
    - Beethoven, Brahms, Bach (C.P.E), and Handel, 1943-1953; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 102)
      Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827. Sonatas, horn, piano, op. 17, F major. Hansen, Conrad, piano. Süddeutscher Rundfunk, live broadcast. 1951 April 19.
      Brahms, Johannes, 1833-1897. Gesänge, women's voices, horns (2), harp, op. 17. Del Mar, Norman, 1919-1994, second horn. Mason, Gwendolyn, harp. Nottingham Oriana Choir; Henderson, Roy, 1899-2000, conductor. 1943 December 30.
      Bach, Carl Philipp Emanuel, 1714-1788. Sonatas, woodwinds, horns (2), H. 629-634. Morris, Gareth, flute. Adeney, Richard, flute. Sutcliffe, Sidney, oboe. James, Natalie, oboe. James, Cecil, 1913-1999, bassoon. London Baroque Ensemble; Haas, Karl, 1900-1970, conductor. 1953 June 18.
      Handel,George Frideric, 1685-1759. Trio Overture in C major. Thurston, Frederick, clarinet. De Peyer, Gervase, 1926-, clarinet. Haas, Karl, 1900-1970, conductor. 1949 December 28.
    - Britten and Sitwell, 1956 June 21; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 103)
      Britten, Benjamin, 1913-1976. The Heart of The Matter. Britten, Benjamin, 1913-1976, piano. Pears, Peter, Sir, tenor. Sitwell, Edith, 1887-1964, narrator. Aldeburgh Festival of Music and the Arts. 1956 June 21. First British broadcast, 1996.
    - Schoeck, Danzi, and Cooke, 1955-1956; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 104)
      Schoeck, Othmar, 1886-1957. Concertos, horn, string orchestra, op. 65. Collegium Musicum Zürich; Sacher, Paul, 1906-1999, conductor. Sveriges radio aktiebolag, live broadcast. 1956 May 4.
      Danzi, Franz, 1763-1826. Concertos, horn, orchestra, P. 239, E major. Kurpfalziches Kamm; Bodart, Eugen, 1905-1981, conductor. 1955 June 1. (Private recording, not the recording copy used for Hans Pizka’s CD HPECD02).
      Cooke, Arnold, 1906-2005. Arioso and Scherzo. Carter Trio. British Broadcasting Corporation, pre-recorded broadcast, 1956 November 3 (pre-recorded 1956 October 30).
    - Lecture Recital - The Early Horn; Britten, Mozart, Bach, Handel, and Vivaldi, 1955; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 105)
      Lecture Recital - The Early Horn. Britten, Benjamin 1913-1976. Nocturne from Serenade, tenor, horn, string orchestra, op. 31.
      Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Duets, horns, K. 487, number 12. Sanders, Neil, horn.
      Bach, Johann Sebastian, 1685-1750. Jagdkantate for soprano, two horns, continuo. Delman, Jacqueline, soprano.
      Handel, George Frideric, 1685-1759. Water music. No. 13, Minuet.
      Vivaldi, Antonio, 1678-1741. Concertos, flutes (2), string orchestra, RV 533, C major; arr. Arranged for two horns. Sanders, Neil, horn. Haydn Orchestra; Newstone, Harry, conductor. British Broadcasting Corporation broadcast. 1955 December 23.
      Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Concertos, horn, orchestra, K. 412, D major. Brain, Dennis, 1921-1957, 1818 Raoux hand horn.
      Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Fragment from Concerto for Horn in E, K98A, 1st performance.
    - Schubert, Gruber, Grainger arrangement, Vinter, and Mozart, 1947-1957; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 106)
      Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828. Auf dem Strom. Delman, Jacqueline, soprano. 1955.
      Gruber, Franz Xaver, 1787-1863. Silent night, holy night. Slater, Lionel, arranger. Schwarzkopf, Elisabeth, soprano. Covent Garden Chorus, Hampstead Parish Church Choir; Pritchard, John, 1921-1989, conductor. Kingsway Hall, London. 1952 October 3. Performance followed by the The First Noel (traditional).
      Grainger, Percy, 1882-1961. British folk-music settings. Irish tune from County Derry, string orchestra. Philharmonia Orchestra (London, England); Weldon, George, conductor.
      Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828. Auf dem Strom. Lewis, Richard, 1914-1990, tenor. Lush, Ernest, piano. Recorded by British Broadcasting Corporation. British Broadcasting Corporation. Third Programme transcription service. 1954 April.
      Vinter, Gilbert. Hunter’s moon. BBC Concert Orchestra; Tausky, Vilem, conductor. British Broadcasting Corporation Home Service, broadcast. 1957 June 16.
      Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Così fan tutte. Cross, Joan. soprano. Philharmonia Orchestra (London, England); Collingwood, Lawrance, conductor. 1947 January 2.
    - Haydn, before 1957; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 107)
      Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809. Concertos, horn, string orchestra, H. VIId, 4, D major. Brain, Alfred, horn.
      Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809. Concertos, horn, string orchestra, H. VIId, 4, D major.
      Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809. Pietà di me. Sutherland, Joan, 1926-2010, soprano. Cantelo, April, soprano. Goldsbrough Orchestra; Mackerras, Charles, 1925-2010, conductor. British Broadcasting Corporation, broadcast. 1956 December 17.
    - Strauss (Richard), 1951-1956; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 108)
      Strauss, Richard, 1864-1949. Concertos, horn, orchestra, no. 1, op. 11, E♭ major. Finnish Radio Symphony Orchestra; Fougstedt, Nils-Eric, 1910-1961, conductor. 1956 October 5.
      Strauss, Richard, 1864-1949. Concertos, horn, orchestra, no. 1, op. 11, E♭ major. Norddeutscher Rundfunk. Sinfonie-Orchester; Schmidt-Isserstedt, Hans, 1900-1973, conductor. Live broadcast. 1954 May 7.
      Strauss, Richard, 1864-1949. Concertos, horn, orchestra, no. 2, E♭ major. BBC Welsh Symphony Orchestra; Jenkins, Rae, conductor. Private recording. 1951 February 5.
    - Wagner, 1954 June 25; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 109)
      Wagner, Richard, 1813-1883. Ring des Nibelungen. Siegfried. Selections. British Broadcasting Corporation, live broadcast. 1954 June 25.
    - Bach, Britten, Haydn, and Mozart, circa 1957; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 110)
      Bach, Johann Sebastian, 1685-1750. Masses, BWV 233, F major. Quoniam tu solus sanctus. Excerpt only. Philharmonia Orchestra (London, England). 1957 February 18.
      Indicated on container inlay - Britten, Benjamin, 1913-1976. Commentary referencing Dennis Brain, hand horn demonstration. This track however is not a commentary by Benjamin Britten referencing Dennis Brain. It is believed to be performance of "Ill Wind" by the comedy duo Flanders and Swann.
      Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809. Symphonies, H. I, 31, D major. Sanders, Neill, horn. Chapman, Edmund, horn. Curse, Alfred, horn. Morris, Gareth, flute. Hurwitz, Emanuel, 1919-2006, violin. Weil, Terence, cello. New Symphony Orchestra; Westrup, J. A. (Jack Allan), 1904-1975, conductor.
      Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Quintets, horn, violin, violas, violoncello, K. 407, E♭major. English String Quartet. 1957 February 18.
    - Mozart, Strauss (Richard), Sieber, and Paiseillo, circa 1947-1955; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 111)
      Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Concertos, horn, orchestra, K. 447, E♭major. Südwestfunk (Baden-Baden, Germany). Orchester; Rosbaud, Hans, 1895-1962, conductor. Live recording at Baden-Baden. 1953 May 6.
      Strauss, Richard, 1864-1949. Concertos, horn, orchestra, no. 2, E♭major.
      Seiber, Mátyás, 1905-1960. Nocturne, horn, string orchestra. London Symphony Orchestra; Cameron, Basil, 1884-1975, conductor. British Broadcasting Corporation. Third Programme, broadcast. 1955 July 29.
      Paisiello, Giovanni, 1740-1816. Nina. Ouverture. Royal Philharmonic Orchestra; Beecham, Thomas, Sir, 1879-1961, conductor. 1947 February 23 and 1947 July 7. Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Concertos, horn, orchestra, K. 417, E♭major. Südwestfunk (Baden-Baden, Germany). Orchester; Rosbaud, Hans, 1895-1962, conductor. Live recording at Baden-Baden. 1953 May 6.
      Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Concertos, horn, orchestra, K. 417, E♭major. Südwestfunk (Baden-Baden, Germany). Orchester; Rosbaud, Hans, 1895-1962, conductor. Live recording at Baden-Baden. 1953 May 6.
    - Beethoven, Handel, Arnell, Mehul, Rossini, Schubert, and Hindemith, 1950-1957; 1 CD-R (Audio 1, Disc 112)
      Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827. Sextets, horns (2), strings, op. 81b, E♭major. Civil, Alan, horn. English String Quartet. British Broadcasting Corporation, live broadcast. 18 February 1957.
      Handel, George Frideric, 1685-1759. Arias, oboes (2), horns (2), bassoon, HWV 410, F major. Cursue, Alfred, horn. London Baroque Ensemble; Haas, Karl, 1900-1970, conductor. 1952 July 15.
      Handel, George Frideric, 1685-1759. Arias, oboes (2), horns (2), bassoon, HWV 411, F major. Cursue, Alfred, horn. London Baroque Ensemble; Haas, Karl, 1900-1970, conductor. 1952 July 15.
      Arnell, Richard, 1917-2009. Serenade, woodwinds, horns (2), double bass, op. 57. Sanders, Neill, horn. Bradley, Francis, horn. Borsdorf, Emil, horn. London Baroque Ensemble; Haas, Karl, 1900-1970, conductor. 1957 May 17.
      Méhul, Etienne Nicolas, 1763-1817. Jeune Henri. Ouverture. Royal Philharmonic Orchestra; Beecham, Thomas, Sir, 1879-1961, conductor. 1953 December 1.
      Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868. Cambiale di matrimonio. Sinfonia. Royal Philharmonic Orchestra; Beecham, Thomas, Sir, 1879-1961, conductor.1950 September 28.
      Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828. Auf dem Strom. Pears, Peter, Sir, tenor. Mewton-Wood, Noel, 1922-1953, piano. British Broadcasting Corporation, live broadcast. 1953 January 28.
      Hindemith, Paul, 1895-1963. Sonata for four horns. Sanders, Neill, horn. Chapman, Edmund, horn. Cursue, Alfred, horn. 1956 January 5.